*The base rate is 2.5%*.
*기준금리 2.5%*.
And it’s staying there.
계속 유지되고 있습니다.
But that feels a little strange, doesn’t it?
그런데 좀 이상하죠.
If rates aren’t going up,
금리가 안 오르면,
then home prices should be rising again.
집값은 다시 올라야 할 것 같습니다.
But in reality,
그런데 현실은,
it’s not that simple.
그렇게 단순하지 않습니다.
Here’s where the market stands right now.
지금 시장은요.
There’s something the market watches,
금리보다 더 민감하게,
even more closely than interest rates.
보는 신호가 따로 있습니다.
Today,
오늘은 그 얘기를,
let’s break that down in simple terms.
쉽게 풀어보겠습니다.
A lot of people think like this:
많은 분들이 이렇게 생각합니다.
If rates aren’t going any higher now,
이제 금리가 더 안 오르는데,
doesn’t that mean real estate should start recovering too?
부동산도 살아나는 거 아니냐.
That’s a completely reasonable thought.
충분히 할 수 있는 생각입니다.
When the base rate stops rising,
실제로 기준금리가 멈추면,
people naturally expect sentiment to improve first.
심리부터 좋아질 것 같거든요.
It feels like the burden of interest payments should ease,
이자 부담이 덜 커질 것 같고,
and buying activity should start picking up again.
매수도 다시 붙을 것 같습니다.
But the market
그런데 시장은,
is colder than people expect.
생각보다 차갑습니다.
It’s hard to say
집값이 전반적으로,
that home prices overall
강하게 반등한다고,
are making a strong comeback.
말하긴 어렵습니다.
Why is that?
왜 그럴까요.
The reason is simple.
이유는 간단합니다.
The market cares less about the *rate pause* itself,
시장은 *금리 동결* 그 자체보다,
and more about what that pause is actually signaling.
그 동결이 뜻하는 상황을,
Let’s start with the bigger picture first.
더 중요하게 보기 때문입니다.
If the base rate stays at 2.5%,
먼저 배경부터 보겠습니다.
that usually means the Bank of Korea
기준금리가 2.5%로 유지된다는 건,
is still watching carefully
한국은행이 지금,
between inflation and the economy.
물가와 경기 사이에서,
Put simply,
더 지켜보겠다는 뜻에 가깝습니다.
the economy isn’t strong enough yet
쉽게 말하면,
to justify a major easing of money.
돈을 확 풀 정도로,
But on the other hand,
경기가 좋은 것도 아닙니다.
inflation isn’t unstable enough
반대로 다시 금리를 올릴 만큼,
to justify another rate hike either.
물가가 불안한 것도 아닙니다.
In other words, we’re in a gray area.
애매한 구간이라는 뜻이죠.
At times like this, people focus less on the fact
이럴 때 사람들은,
that rates have paused,
금리가 멈췄다는 사실보다,
and more on whether their income will rise,
앞으로 내 소득이 늘지,
whether the economy will really recover,
경기가 정말 살아날지,
and whether they can actually afford to buy a home right now.
지금 집을 사도 버틸 수 있을지,
That’s the first calculation they make.
이걸 먼저 계산합니다.
In the end, the market
결국 시장은,
doesn’t just look at one rate number.
금리 숫자 하나가 아니라,
It looks at your *ability to hold up* going forward.
앞으로의 *버틸 힘*을 봅니다.
And here’s something important.
여기서 중요한 게 있습니다.
What really matters is the *mortgage rate*.
바로 *대출금리*입니다.
A lot of people
많은 분들이,
only look at the base rate.
기준금리만 봅니다.
But when you’re buying a home,
하지만 집을 살 때,
what you actually feel
실제로 체감하는 건,
isn’t the base rate itself.
기준금리가 아닙니다.
What matters more is
내가 은행에서,
how much you can borrow
얼마에 빌릴 수 있느냐.
and at what rate from the bank.
이게 더 중요합니다.
Even if the base rate stays the same,
기준금리가 그대로여도,
if actual mortgage rates
실제 주택담보대출 금리가,
don’t come down quickly,
빨리 내려가지 않으면,
buyer sentiment won’t recover easily.
매수 심리는 살아나기 어렵습니다.
That’s because banks
왜냐하면 은행은,
don’t set lending rates
기준금리만 보고,
based only on the base rate.
대출금리를 정하지 않기 때문입니다.
They also have to consider funding costs,
은행 조달비용도 봐야 하고,
added spreads get layered on,
가산금리도 붙고,
and regulations come into play too.
각종 규제도 같이 작동합니다.
Especially rules like *stress DSR*,
특히 *스트레스 DSR* 같은 규제는,
which can directly change
대출 가능 금액 자체를,
how much you’re allowed to borrow.
바꿔버립니다.
So people
그러니까 사람들은,
don’t buy homes
기준금리 2.5%라는 숫자만 보고,
just because they see a 2.5% base rate.
집을 사는 게 아닙니다.
What matters is
내가 실제로,
how much they can actually borrow,
얼마를 빌릴 수 있는지.
and how much interest
매달 이자를,
they’ll have to pay every month.
얼마나 내야 하는지.
That number matters more.
그 숫자가 더 중요합니다.
The market always
시장은 늘,
responds to the rate people actually feel.
체감 금리에 반응합니다.
More than the rate in the headlines,
뉴스 속 금리보다,
it reacts to the pressure in your bank account.
통장 속 부담에 반응합니다.
The next thing to watch
다음으로 봐야 할 건,
is *transaction volume*.
*거래량*입니다.
This indicator really matters.
이 지표가 정말 중요합니다.
From the outside, prices
가격은 겉으로 보면,
can look like they’re holding up.
버티는 것처럼 보일 수 있습니다.
Listings may not be falling,
호가도 안 떨어지고,
and distressed sales may even seem to be fading.
급매도 줄어든 것처럼 보일 수 있죠.
But if transaction volume doesn’t recover,
그런데 거래량이 살아나지 않으면,
the market is still running cold.
시장 체온은 아직 낮습니다.
Put simply,
쉽게 말해,
prices may be standing still,
가격은 서 있는데,
but people still aren’t actually buying.
사람들이 실제로 안 사고 있다는 뜻입니다.
And that matters a lot.
이건 굉장히 중요합니다.
Because in the end,
왜냐하면 시장의 방향은,
the direction of the market is revealed by actual transactions.
결국 거래가 말해주기 때문입니다.
Not by talk,
말이 아니라,
but by deals getting done.
체결이 말해줍니다.
Not by the mood,
분위기가 아니라,
but by actual buying behavior.
매수 행동이 말해줍니다.
If transaction volume doesn’t back it up,
거래량이 받쳐주지 않으면,
a price rebound won’t spread broadly.
가격 반등은 넓게 퍼지기 어렵습니다.
Prices may hold for a while,
잠깐 버틸 수는 있어도,
but it’s hard for that to turn into a trend.
추세가 되긴 어렵습니다.
Especially end-users
특히 실수요자는,
are much more cautious than before.
예전보다 훨씬 더 꼼꼼합니다.
They don’t just look at rates.
금리만 보지 않습니다.
They check how much they can borrow,
대출 가능 금액을 보고,
look at local supply conditions,
지역별 공급도 보고,
and watch the direction of lease prices too.
전세가격 흐름도 같이 봅니다.
If I buy this home,
내가 이 집을 샀을 때,
will jeonse demand support the price?
전세가 받쳐주는지.
Is there a large number of new units coming in?
입주 물량이 많은지.
Not just whether prices will rise,
앞으로 가격이 아니라,
but whether the cash flow makes sense.
현금흐름이 괜찮은지.
They look at all of that together.
이걸 같이 봅니다.
So just because a few preferred areas
그러니까 일부 선호 지역이,
are holding up or going higher,
버티거나 오른다고 해서,
it’s hard to say right away
전체 시장이 살아났다고,
that the whole market is recovering.
바로 말하긴 어렵습니다.
Looking at the market as a whole,
전체 시장으로 보면,
it’s hard to say
금리 동결만으로,
that a bull market has started
상승장이 시작됐다고 보기 어렵습니다.
just because rates have paused.
그 정도로 지금 시장은,
That’s how selective
훨씬 더 선별적으로 움직입니다.
today’s market has become.
사례를 떠올려보면,
If you think of actual examples,
더 분명합니다.
it becomes even clearer.
같은 금리 환경에서도,
Even under the same rate environment,
서울 핵심지와 외곽은,
prime areas in Seoul and the outskirts
반응이 다릅니다.
react differently.
수도권과 지방도,
react differently too.
수요가 몰리는 곳은,
In places where demand is concentrated,
거래가 조금만 붙어도,
even a small pickup in transactions
가격이 버팁니다.
can help prices hold up.
사고 싶은 사람이,
Because those are places
원래 많은 곳이기 때문입니다.
people already want to buy.
반대로 수요가 약한 곳은,
On the other hand, in weaker-demand areas,
금리가 멈춰도,
even if rates pause,
거래가 잘 붙지 않습니다.
transactions still don’t pick up easily.
사고 싶은 사람보다,
Because there are more people hesitating
망설이는 사람이 많기 때문입니다.
than people eager to buy.
여기서 시장의 본질이 보입니다.
And that reveals the core of the market.
지금 시장은,
Right now,
금리 하나로,
this is not a market
같이 움직이는 장이 아닙니다.
where everything moves together
*자금 여력*과,
based on rates alone.
*입지*에 따라,
It’s a market splitting apart
갈라지는 장입니다.
based on *purchasing power*
한마디로,
and *location*.
선별 장세에 가깝습니다.
In short,
좋은 곳은 버티고,
it’s a highly selective market.
약한 곳은 계속 조심스럽습니다.
Strong areas hold up,
이 차이가 점점 더 커집니다.
while weaker areas remain cautious.
그래서 지금은,
And that gap is only getting wider.
질문을 바꿔야 합니다.
So now,
금리가 멈췄는데,
we need to change the question.
왜 집값이 안 오르지.
Rates have paused,
이 질문도 중요합니다.
so why aren’t home prices rising?
하지만 더 중요한 질문은,
That’s an important question too.
어디가 먼저 반응하느냐입니다.
But the more important question is:
누가 먼저 움직이느냐입니다.
which areas respond first?
현금 여력이 있는 수요가,
Who moves first?
어느 지역에 붙는지.
Where demand with real cash capacity
대출이 실제로 풀리는 구간이,
starts coming back first,
어디인지.
where lending is actually loosening in practice,
전세가가 받쳐주는 곳이,
where lease prices are providing support,
어딘지.
and where supply pressure is lower.
공급 부담이 적은 곳이,
The market now
이걸 봐야 합니다.
can’t be explained
이제 시장은,
by a one-line headline anymore.
한 줄 뉴스로 설명되지 않습니다.
There was a time
기준금리 한 줄로,
when one line about the base rate
전체가 움직이던 시기가 있었죠.
could move the whole market.
하지만 지금은 아닙니다.
But not anymore.
지금은 훨씬 복합적입니다.
Now the picture is much more complex.
금리와 대출,
Interest rates and lending,
거래량과 수급,
transaction volume and supply-demand,
그리고 경기 기대가,
and expectations for the economy
같이 움직입니다.
are all moving together.
특히 경기 기대는,
And especially expectations for the economy
절대 가볍지 않습니다.
should never be taken lightly.
사람들은 집을 살 때,
When people buy a home,
가격만 보지 않습니다.
they don’t just look at the price.
앞으로 내 직장이 안정적인지,
They also think about
소득이 유지될지,
whether their job will stay stable,
갑자기 지출이 늘진 않을지,
whether their income will hold up,
이런 것도 같이 봅니다.
and whether unexpected expenses might rise.
기준금리가 그대로라고 해도,
Even if the base rate stays the same,
경기에 대한 확신이 약하면,
if confidence in the economy is weak,
큰 대출을 일으키기 어렵습니다.
it’s hard to take on a big loan.
이건 아주 현실적인 판단입니다.
That’s a very realistic judgment.
지금은 공격적으로 들어가기보다,
Right now, instead of jumping in aggressively,
확실한 신호를 기다리는 사람이 많습니다.
a lot of people are waiting for clearer signals.
그래서 시장이,
That’s why the market
생각보다 천천히 움직입니다.
is moving more slowly than expected.
겉으로는 조용한데,
On the surface, it looks quiet,
속에서는 아주 예민하게,
but underneath,
신호를 고르고 있는 겁니다.
it’s choosing signals very carefully.
또 하나 봐야 할 건,
There’s one more thing to watch,
심리의 방향입니다.
and that’s the direction of sentiment.
부동산 시장은,
The real estate market
늘 기대와 불안이 같이 갑니다.
always moves with both hope and anxiety.
금리 동결은 분명,
A rate pause is definitely
나쁜 뉴스만은 아닙니다.
not all bad news.
그렇다고 바로,
But at the same time,
강한 호재도 아닙니다.
it’s not immediately
왜냐하면 동결이라는 건,
a strong positive signal either.
좋아서 멈춘 것일 수도 있지만,
Because a pause can mean
아직 확신이 없어서,
things are stable enough to stop,
멈춘 것일 수도 있기 때문입니다.
but it can also mean
지금 시장은,
policymakers still aren’t confident enough
후자에 더 가깝게 해석합니다.
to make the next move.
좋아서 달리는 장이라기보다,
And right now,
조심스럽게 확인하는 장입니다.
the market is leaning more toward that second interpretation.
그래서 반응도,
This isn’t a market charging ahead with confidence,
지역별로 나뉘고,
but one moving carefully and checking as it goes.
수요층별로 나뉘고,
That’s why the response
가격대별로도 나뉩니다.
is split by region,
정리해보겠습니다.
split by buyer group,
*기준금리 2.5% 유지* 자체는,
and even split by price range.
무조건 호재도 아니고,
Let’s sum it up.
무조건 악재도 아닙니다.
*Keeping the base rate at 2.5%*
오히려 시장이 아직,
isn’t automatically bullish,
확신을 못 갖고 있다는,
and it isn’t automatically bearish either.
신호에 가깝습니다.
If anything, it’s closer to
집값을 움직이는 건 이제,
a signal that the market
기준금리 한 줄이 아닙니다.
still doesn’t have conviction.
*대출금리*가 중요하고,
What moves home prices now
*거래량*이 중요하고,
is no longer just one line about the base rate.
지역별 *수급*이 중요합니다.
*Mortgage rates* matter,
그리고 경기 회복에 대한,
*transaction volume* matters,
*기대*도 중요합니다.
and local *supply and demand* matters.
결국 지금은,
And expectations
금리만 보는 시각보다,
for an economic recovery
시장이 어디에서,
also matter.
먼저 반응하는지 읽는 시각이,
In the end, right now,
훨씬 중요합니다.
it matters far more
뉴스 headline보다,
to read where the market
현장의 흐름을 봐야 합니다.
starts responding first
숫자 한 개보다,
than to focus on rates alone.
연결된 신호를 같이 봐야 합니다.
More than the headline,
그래야 지금 시장을,
you need to watch what’s happening on the ground.
조금 더 정확하게 볼 수 있습니다.
More than any single number,
여러분 지역은 어떻습니까.
you need to watch how the signals connect.
거래가 조금씩 살아나고 있나요.
That’s how you can read
아니면 아직 조용한가요.
today’s market
여러분 지역은,
more accurately.
어떤 영향을 받고 있는지,
What’s your area like right now?
댓글로 남겨주세요.